[
    {
        "question": "To boost industrial growth government provides electricity, water, taxes at a …………… rate.",
        "options": [
            "Faster",
            "Higher",
            "Concessional"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "The availability of …………… manpower is the most important reason for information technology industry",
        "options": [
            "Skilled",
            "Unskilled",
            "Labour"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "The finished products have an added value because they are more …………… .",
        "options": [
            "Elastic",
            "Durable",
            "Beautiful"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": " Identify the non-advantages factor of industrial development.",
        "options": [
            "Energy",
            "Minerals",
            "Pollutions",
            "Water supply"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "Identify the odd one out :",
        "options": [
            "Raw material",
            "Land",
            "Labour",
            "Finished products"
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "question": "Identify the industries : Pickle making, Jam and Jelly making, jaggery making, fruit processing.",
        "options": [
            "Agro-based",
            "Mineral based",
            "Raw material based"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "Paper making is ……………. Type of industry",
        "options": [
            "Medium",
            "Large",
            "Small"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "Name the industry Cotton, Threading, Dyeing, Weaving",
        "options": [
            "Readymade garments",
            "Fashion",
            "Textile"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "Which basic raw material is required for this Biscuits making, Jelly making, Jam making, Cake making",
        "options": [
            "Salt",
            "Sugar",
            "Nuts"
        ],
        "answer": 2 
    },
    {
        "question": "For engineering industries the raw material is …………… .",
        "options": [
            "Machinery",
            "Iron-rods",
            "Spare-parts"  
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "Name the industry : Fruit orchards, labour, excellent transport facilities water supply, electricity, market",
        "options": [
            "Food processing",
            "Fruit processing",
            "Juice making"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "Write the full form of M.I.D.C.",
        "options": [
            "Maharashtra Industrial Development Corporation.",
            "Maharashtra Transport Development Corporation.",
            " Maharashtra Agricultural Development Corporation"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not an IT centre.",
        "options": [
            "Mumbai",
            "Delhi",
            "Nagpur",
            "Pune"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "True / False It is compulsory for individual or group of industries to spend 2% of their profit for the betterment of the society.",
        "options": [
            "True",
            "False"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "M.I.D.C. was established in the year …………… .",
        "options": [
            "1975",
            "1955",
            "1962"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "Identify the type of industry. → improved lifestyle = ……………  Oil extracting, pot making, papad making, handicraft.",
        "options": [
            "Small industry",
            "Medium industry",
            "Heavy industry"
        ],
        "answer": 1 
    },
    {
        "question": "The available raw material is process into …………… products.",
        "options": [
            "Complete",
            "Finished",
            "Incomplete"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "Iron and steel industry requires raw material and ……………. .",
        "options": [
            "Iron",
            "Energy",
            "Steel"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "Agro-based industries are mostly located in …………… areas.",
        "options": [
            "Urban",
            "Town",
            "Rural"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "…………… is famous for iron and steel industry",
        "options": [
            "Nagpur",
            "Jamshedpur",
            "Tarapur"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "Industries or manufacturing units provide …………… occupation.",
        "options": [
            "Secondary",
            "Primary",
            "Tertiary"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "Name the Industry Computers, Laptops, Mobiles, Internet.",
        "options": [
            "Information Technology",
            "Information Devices",
            "Information Software"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    }
]